在前面一节我们讨论了模逆 我们说过
In the previous segment we talked about
modular inversion and we said the Euclid's
欧几里德算法给了我们一个有效的寻找元素N的模逆的方式
algorithm gives us an efficient way to
find the inverse of an element modulo N.
在这一节我们将按时间顺序继续向后看
In this segment we're going to forward
through time and we're going to move to
我们来到17、18世纪 我们将要讨论费马和欧拉的贡献的年代
the seventeenth and eighteenth century
where we're going to talk about
在此之前 让我们快速复习一下上一节所讨论的内容
Fermat and Euler contributions.
Before that let's do a quick review of
向往常一样 我将会用N代表正整数
what we discussed in the previous segment.
So as usual I'm going to let N denote the
N也可以说是一个N位的正整数
positive integer and let's just say that N
happens to be a n-bit integer, in other
换句话说 它在2^n和2^(n+1)之间 同样 我用P代表素数
words it's between two to the n and two to
the n+1, as usual we're going to let P
现在我们说ZN是是一个从0到N-1的整数集合
denote a prime. Now we said that
ZN is a set of integers from zero
我们可以在模N的意义下对集合中度元素进行加法和乘法
to N-1 and we said that we can add and
multiply elements in the set modulo N. We
我们也说过ZN^*是集合ZN中全体可逆元素的集合
also said that ZN star is basically the
set of invertible elements in ZN. And we
我们证明过一个简单的引理 如果x与n互质那么X是可逆的
proved a simple lemma to say that, X is
invertible if and only if X is relatively
我们不仅明白了什么样的元素是可逆的什么样的是不可逆的
prime to N. And not only did we
completely understand which elements are
我们也给出了一个十分有效的建立在欧几里德扩展算法上面的算法
invertible and which aren't, we also
showed a very efficient algorithm based on
去在ZN中找到一个元素X的逆
Euclid's extended algorithm, to find the
inverse of an element X in ZN. And we said
我们说过 这个算法的复杂度是O(n^2)
that the running time of this algorithm,
is basically order n squared, where
n是大写字母N的位数 好的 像我之前所说的
again, n is the number of bits of the
number capital N. So as I said, now
我们将从古希腊时代来到17世纪
we're going to move from Greek times all
the way to the seventeenth century and
讨论费马 费马提出了很多十分重要的理论
talk about Fermat. So Fermat did a number
of important theorems. The one that I want
我今天想给大家看的其中之一就是 假设我给大家一个素数P
to show you here today is the following.
So suppose I give you a prime P. Then in
然后事实上在ZP*中任何一个元素 如果我研究X^(p-1)
fact for any element X in ZP star, it so
happens that if I look at X and raise it
我将会在ZP中得到1 好的 现在让我们来快速的看一个例子
to the power of P - 1, I'm a gonna get
one, in ZP. So let's look at a quick
假设我让P等于5 然后我来研究3^(P-1)
example. Suppose I set the number P to be
five. And I look at, three to the power of
换句话说 3^4 是81
P-1. In other words, three to the power of
four, Three to the power of four is 81,
事实上 在模5的意义下它是1 这个例子满足了费马定理
which in fact, is one modulo five. This
example satisfies Fermat's theorem.
有趣的是 事实上费马自己并没有证明这个定理
Interestingly, Fermat actually didn't prove this theorem himself. The proof
这个定理实际上要等到欧拉在将近100年之后才被证明
actually waited until Euler, who
proved that almost 100 years later. And in
事实上 他证明了这个定理的更具有普适性的一个版本
fact, he proved a much more general
version of this theorem. So let's look at
让我们来看一下费马定理的一个简单应用 假设我在ZP*里寻找到一个元素X
a simple application of Fermat's theorem.
Suppose I look at an element X in Z P
我想要提醒大家这里的P必须是素数 那么 现在我们知道什么
star. And I want to remind you here that P
[inaudible] must be a prime. Well, then what do we
我们知道X^(P-1)=1 我们可以把X^(P-1)
know? We know that X to the P minus one is
equal to one. Well, we can write X to the
写成X*X^(P-2) 那么现在我们知道了
P minus one as X times X to the power of P
minus two. Well so now we know that X
X*X^(P-2)正好是1
times X to the power of P minus two
happens to be equal to one. And what that
也就是说 X^(P-2)就是X模P的逆
says, is that really the inverse of X
modulo P, is simply X to the P minus two.
这给了我们另一种找X模素数的逆的算法
So this gives us another algorithm for
finding the inverse of X modulo a prime.
计算X^(P-2) 就会得到X的逆
Simply raise X to the power of p minus
two, and that will give us the inverse of
事实上这是一个寻找模素数的逆的好方法
x. It turns out, actually this is a fine
way to compute inverses modulo a prime.
但是与欧几里德算法相比她有两点不足 第一
But it has two deficiencies compared to
Euclid's algorithm. First of all, it only
它仅仅适用于模素数 而欧几里德算法还适用于模合数
works modulo primes, Whereas, Euclid's
algorithm worked modulo composites as
第二 事实上这个算法的效率是比较低的
well. And second of all, it turns out this
algorithm is actually less efficient. When
当我们讨论如何计算模指数时 我们将会在本章最后一节讨论
we talk about how to do modular
exponentiations--we're gonna do that in
大家会看的计算这个指数的算法复杂度
the last segment in this module--you'll
see that the running time to compute this
事实上是P的大小的立方 所以这将会花掉大约（log P）^3的时间
exponentiation is actually cubic in the
size of P. So this will take roughly log
如果大家还记得 欧几里德算法可以在P的平方的时间里
cube of P, whereas if you remember,
Euclid's algorithm was able to compute the
计算出逆
inverse in quadratic time in the
representation of P. So not only is this
所以这个算法不仅使用于素数不具有普适性 而且不是那么有效
algorithm less general it only works for
primes, it's also less efficient. So score
所以欧几里德赢了 但是 这个关于素数的定理是极其重要的
one for Euclid. But nevertheless, this
fact about primes is extremely important,
我们将在未来的几周里大量用的它
and we're gonna be making extensive use of
it in the next couple of weeks. So let me
所以让我给大家快速的看一个费马定理的简单应用
show you a quick and simple application
for Fermat's theorem suppose we wanted
假设我们想生成一个大的随机素数 比如我们的素数要有1000位之类的长度
to generate a large random prime, say our
prime needed to be 1,000 bits or so. So
我们寻找的这个素数的量级在2^1024
the prime we're looking for is on the
order of two to the 1024 [inaudible]. So here's
这是一个非常简单的概率定理 我们将要做的就是
a very simple probabilistic algorithm.
What we would do is we would choose a
从一个给定的区间里随机选择一个整数 然后我们会检测
random integer in the interval that was
specified. And then we would test whether
这个整数是否满足费马定理 换句话说 我们会用以2为底的数检测
this integer satisfies Fermat's theorem.
In other words, we would test for example
我们将会检测2^(P-1)在Z p中是否为1
using the base two; we would test whether
two to the power of p minus one equals one
如果答案是否定的 等式不相等 那么我们可以
in Z p. If the answer is no, then if this
equality doesn't hold, then we know for
确定我们选择的p不是素数 如果这发生了 我们只好
sure that the number p that we chose is
not a prime. And if that happens, all we
回到第一步 换另一个素数 我们一遍遍的重复
do is we go back to step one and we try
another prime. And we do this again and
直到找到一个整数满足条件
again and again, until finally we find an
integer that satisfies this condition. And
一旦我们找到整数满足这个条件 我们简单的输出它并停下来
once we find an integer that satisfies
this condition, we simply output it and
这结束了  这事实上比较难以证明
stop. Now it turns out, this is actually a
fairly difficult statement to prove. But
但如果一个随机数通过测试 这很有可能是一个素数
it turns out if a random number passes
this test, then it's extremely likely to
特别的 P不是素数的可能性很小
be a prime. In particular the probability
that P is not a prime is very small. It's
小于2的-60次方 对1024比特范围的数
like less than two to the -60 for the
range of 1024 bit numbers. As the
随着数越来越大 通过测试但不是素数的可能性
number gets bigger and bigger the
probability that it passes this test here,
很快降到0 所以这是一个很有意思的算法
but is not a prime drops to zero very
quickly. So this is actually quite an
你会发觉我们不保证输出一定是
interesting algorithm. You realize we're
not guaranteed that the output is in fact
素数 我们只知道它很可能是一个素数
a prime. All we know is that it's very,
very likely to be a prime. In other words
换言之 他不是素数意味着我们很不幸运
the only way that it's not a prime is that
we got extremely unlucky. In fact so
事实上不幸到一个可以忽略可能性的事件发生了
unlucky that a negligible probability
event just happened. Another way to say
另一个说法是 如果你看1024整数的序列 然后 这是素数的序列
this is that if you look at the set of all
1024 integers, then, well, there's the set
我在这写素数 然后这是一些合数
of primes. Let me write prime here. And
then there is a small number of
这事实上会错误的通过测试 我们把错误的素数叫做F
composites. That actually will falsify the
test. Let's call them F for false primes.
我们把他们叫做FP 对错误的素数 又很少的合数
Let's call them FP, for false primes.
There's a very small number of composites
不是素数却会通过测试 但既然我们选择的是随机整数
that are not prime and yet will pass this
test. But as we choose random integers,
你看 我们在这里选择一个 这选一个 这样 当我们随机选数
you know, we choose one here, one here,
one here, and so on, as we choose random
我们选到错误素数的可能性很小
integers, the probability that we fall
into the set of false primes is so small
以至于我们可以忽略这个事件 换言之 我们可以证明
That it's essentially a negligible event
that we can ignore. In other words, one
错误素数的序列是相当小的 一个随机的选择
can prove that the set of false primes is
extremely small, and a random choice is
不可能导致这样一个错误素数 现在我应该提到 事实上 有一个非常简单的
unlikely to pick such a false prime. Now I
should mention, in fact, this is a very
算法生成素数 事实上 到现在为止不是最好的算法
simple algorithm for generating primes.
It's actually, by far, not the best
我们现在有好的多的算法 事实上 一旦你有一个备选的素数
algorithm. We have much better algorithms
now. And, in fact, once you have a
我们有非常高效的算法能
candidate prime, we now have very
efficient algorithms that will actually
明确证明这个备选素数是否真的是一个素数
prove beyond a doubt that this candidate
prime really is a prime. So we don't even
所以我们不用依赖于可能性状态 但费马测试是
have to rely on probabilistic statements.
But nevertheless, this Fermat test is so
那么简单 以至于我就想要展示给你们这是一个生成素数的很简单的方法
simple, that I just wanted to show you
that it's an easy way to generate primes.
尽管事实上素数不是这么生成的 最后一点
Although in reality, this is not how
primes are generated. As the last point,
我想你们可能想知道 这个迭代需要重复多少次
I'll say that you might be wondering how
many times this iteration has to repeat
我们才能真正找到这个素数 这是一个经典的结果
until we actually find the prime. And
that's actually a classic result; it's
被叫做素数定理 是这样描述的 在几百次迭代后
called the prime number theorem, which
says that, after a few hundred iterations,
我们有很大概率找到素数 也就是说
in fact, we'll find the prime with
high probability. So in expectation, one would
你需要准备几百次迭代而不是更多 现在我们理解了费马定理
expect a few hundred iterations and no
more. Now that we understand
我想说的下一个点是讨论ZP星结构
Fermat's theorem, the next thing I want
to talk about is what's called the
所以这里我们要向后看100年到十八世纪
structure of ZP star. So here, we are
going to move 100 years into the future...
看看欧拉的工作 欧拉展示的第一作品
Into the eighteenth century and look at
the work of Euler. And one of the first
是现在被称为ZP星曾被叫做
things Euler showed is in modern language
is that ZP star is what's called a
循环群 ZP星是循环圈是什么意思呢？ 它意味着在
cyclic group. What does it mean that ZP
star is a cyclic group? What it means is
ZP星中存在一些元素G 如果我们取G
that there exists some element G in ZP
star, such that if we take G and raise to
取一串G的幂次项 G方根 G平方 G四次 。。。
a bunch of powers G, G squared, G cubed, G
to the fourth. And so on and so forth up
直到我们得到G的P-2次 注意 不可能到G的P-2次外
until we reach G to the P minus two.
Notice there's no point of going beyond G
因为G的P-1次 依据费马定理等于1
to the p minus two, because G to the p
minus one by Fermat's theorem is equal to
所以我们会循环回一 如果我们回到G的p-1次
one, so then we will cycle back to one. If
we go back to G to the p minus one, then G
那么G的p次会等于G G的P-1次会等于G方根
to the p will be equal to G, G to the p
plus one will be equal to G squared, and
这样 我们事实上得到一个循环 如果我们继续取G的更高次
so on and so forth. So we'll actually get
a cycle if we keep raising to higher and
那么我们不如在G的P-2次停下来
higher powers of G. So we might as well
stop at the power of G to the p minus two.
欧拉展示的是 事实上有一个G如果你观察
And what Euler showed is that in fact
there is an element G such that if you
其所有幂次拓展称为ZP星
look at all of its powers all of its
powers expand the entire group ZP Star.
G的幂次个我们所有ZP星中的元素 这样的元素
The powers of G give us all the elements
in ZP star. Elements of this, of this type
我们称之为一个生成元 G是ZP星的一个生成元
is called a generator. So G would be said
to be a generator of ZP star. So let's
让我们快速的看一个例子 让P等于7
look at a quick example. So let's look,
for example, at P equals seven. And let's
我们来看一个简单的例子。例如，p=7
look at all the powers of three. So three
squared three cubed, three to the fourth,
我们看3的所有幂。3^2,3^3,3^4,
three to the fifth, Three to the six,
already we know, is equal to one modular
3^5,3^6,由费马小定理，我们已经知道
seven by Fermat's Theorem. So there's no
point in looking at three to the six. We
3^6=1 mod 7.所以没有必要看3^6了
know we would just get one. So here, I
calculated all these powers for you, and I
我们知道它会是1.这里我给大家计算了所有这些幂
wrote them out. And you see that in fact,
we get all the numbers [inaudible] in Z,
我写下它们，大家可以看到我们得到了（Z_7）*里
in Z7 star. In other words, we get
one, two, three, four, five, and six. So
所有的数。换句话说，我们获得了1.2.3.4.5.6
we would say that three is a generator of
Z7 star. Now I should point out that not
所以我们说，3是Z_7^*的一个生成元。现在我应该指出
every element is a generator. For example,
if we look at all the powers of two, well,
不是每个元素都是生成元。例如，如果我们看2的所有幂
that's not gonna generate the entire
group. In particular, if we look at two to
那不会生成整个群。特别地，如果我们看2^0
the zero, we get one. Two to the one, we
get two. Two squared is four, and two
会得到1，2^1=2,2^2=4
cubed is eight, which is one modular
seven. So we cycled back and then two to
2^3=8=1 mod 7,所以我们循环回来了
the fourth would be two, two to the fifth
would be four. And so on and so forth. So
那么2^4=2,2^5=4...等等
if we look at the powers of two, we just
get one, two, and four. We don't get the
那么如果我们看2的各个幂，我们只能获得1，2，4
whole group and therefore we say that two
is not a generator of Z7 star. Now again,
我们不能获得整个群，因此我们说2不是Z_7^*的生成元
something that we'll use very often is
given an element G of ZP, if we look at a
一个很常用的是，给定Z_p^*里的一个元素g
set of all powers of G, the resulting set
is gonna be called the group generated by
如果我们看g的全体幂组成的集合，得到的集合就叫做g的生成群
G, okay? So these are all the powers of G.
They give us what's called a
这些都是g的幂
multiplicative group. Again, the technical
term doesn't matter. The point is we're
他们给了我们一个乘法群。这些技术术语并不重要
gonna call all these powers of G, the
group generated by G. In fact there's this
重要的是，我们把所有这些g的幂，叫做g的生成群
notation which I don't use very often,
angle G angle, to denote this group that's
事实上这个记号我们不会经常使用：
generated by G. And then we call the order
of G in Z p star, we simply let that be
表示g的生成群，然后，我们把g的生成群的大小
the size of the group that's generated by
G. So in other words, the order of G in Z
叫做g在Z_p^*里的阶。换句话说
p star is the size of this group. But
another way to think about that is
g在Z_p^*里的阶等于的大小。另一种思考的方法是
basically it's the smallest integer A such
that G to the A is equal to one in Z P.
g的阶是满足在Z_p中，g^a=1的最小的整数a
Okay, it's basically the smallest power
that causes the power of G to be equal to
是最小的次数，导致g的幂等于1
one. And it's very easy to see that this
equality here basically if we look at all
非常容易看出这个等式。如果我们看g的所有幂
the powers of G and we look at one, G, G
squared, G cubed and so on and so forth up
我们看1，g,g^2,g^3....
until we get to G to the order of G minus
one. And then if we look at the order of G
直到我们得到g^(|-1|)。然后如果我们看
to the order of G. This thing is simply
going to be equal to one, by definition.
g^||，根据定义，g^||=1
Okay, so there's no point in looking at
any higher powers. We might as well just
好，再看更高的点没有意义了
stop raising to powers here. And as a
result the size of the set, in fact, is
这里我们可以停止升幂次了。因此这个集合的大小
the order of G. And you can see that the
order is the smallest power such that
事实上就是g的阶。大家可以看到这个阶是最小的幂次
raising G to that power gives us one in Z
p. So I hope this is clear although it
满足对应的g的幂在Z_p中等于1.那么我希望说清楚了
might take a little bit of thinking to
absorb all this notation. But in the
理解所有的这些记号需要费些功夫
meantime let's look at a few examples. So,
again, let's fix our, our prime to be
同时我们看几个例子，我们固定质素为7
seven. And let's look at the order of the
number of elements. So what is the order
我们看其各个元素的阶
of three modulus of seven? Well, we're
asking what is the size of the group that
3 mod 7的阶是多少？我们在问3模7的生成群的大小
three generates modulus of seven? Well, we
said that three is a generator of Z7 star.
我们说过，3是Z_7^*的一个生成元
So it generates all of Z7 star. There are
six elements in Z7 star. And therefore we
所以它生成了Z_7^*的全部元素。Z_7^*里共有6个元素
say that the order of three is equal to
six. Similarly, I can ask, well, what is
所以3的阶等于6.类似的，我可以问
the order of two modulo seven? And in
fact, we already saw the answer. So let's,
2模7的阶是多少？事实上，我们已经见过答案了
I'll ask you, what is the order of two
modulo seven and see if you can f igure
我问大家，2模7的阶是多少？看看大家能否解出答案
out what this answer is. So the answer is
three and again, the reason is if we look
那么答案是3，原因是如果我们看
at the set of powers of two modulo seven,
we have one, two, two squared, and then
2模7的幂组成的集合，我们有1，2，2^2
two cubed is already equal to one. So this
is the entire set of powers of two modulo
然后2^3又是1了。所以这些就是2模7的所有幂
seven. There are only three of them and,
therefore, the order of two modulo seven
只有三个，因此2模7的阶是3
is exactly three. Now let me ask you a
trick question. What's the order of one
我问大家一个有点难的问题:1模7的阶是多少？
modulo seven? Well, the answer is one.
Because if you look at the group that's
答案是1，因为大家看1的生成群
generated by one, well, there's only one
number in that group, namely the number
只有一个数在1的生成群里，即数1
one. If I raise one to a whole bunch of
powers, I'm always gonna get one, And
如果我计算1的一组幂，我总是得到1
therefore the order of 1 modulo 7
In fact the order of 1 modulo any prime
所以1模7的阶是1，事实上，1模任意质数的阶
is always gonna be 1. Now there's an
important theorem of Lagrange, that
总是1.现在有重要的拉格朗日定理
actually this is a very, very special case
of it, what I am stating here. But
我这里说的仅仅是拉格朗日定理的一个特例
Langrage's theorem basically implies that
if you look at the order of G modulo p,
拉格朗日定理意味着，如果你看g模p的阶
the order is always going to divide P-1. So in our two example you see,
这个阶始终整除p-1。那么在我们给大家的两个例子中
six divides seven minus one, six divides
six, and similarly, three divides seven
6整除7-1，即6整除6，类似地，3整除7-1
minus one. Namely again three divides six.
But this is very general; your order is
即3整除6.但这是很一般的
always going be a factor of P minus one.
In fact, I'll tell you, maybe it's a
你的阶始终是p-1的因子。事实上，我会告诉你
puzzle for you to think about. It's
actually very easy to deduce Fermat's
也许你会想想这个谜题,由拉格朗日定理的这个事实
theorem directly from this fact, from this
Lagrange's theorem in fact. And so
某种意义上来说，费马定理是拉格朗日定理的直接推导
Fermat's theorem really in some sense
follows directly from Lagrange's theorem.
顺便说一句，拉格朗日工作在十九世纪
Lagrange, by the way, did his work in the
nineteenth century, so you can already see
所以我们可以看到我们是怎么沿着历史前进的，我们从古希腊出发
how we're making progress through time. We
started in Greek times, and already we
然后我们结束于十九世纪，我可以告诉大家更多的是
ended up in the nineteenth century. And I
can tell you that more advanced crypto
更先进的密码学在二十世纪时被广泛的运用
actually uses twentieth century math very
extensively. Now that we understand the
既然现在我们已经了解了Z-p^*的结构，让我们把它推广的合数
structure of ZP star, let's generalize
that to composites, and look at the
并看看Z-n^*的结构，我想展示给你们什么是欧拉定理
structure of ZN star. So what I wanna show
you here is what's called Euler's Theorem
欧拉定理是费马定理的一个直接推广，所以欧拉定理定义如下函数
which is a, a direct generalization of
Fermat's Theorem. So, Euler defined the
给定一个整数N，欧拉定义了一个函数φ
following function. So given an integer N,
he defined what's called the phi
函数φ（M），是Z_N^*的大小
function, phi of M, to be
basically the size of the set ZN star.
有时也称为欧拉的φ函数，Z_N^*的大小
This is sometimes called, Euler's phi
function. The size of the set Z N star. So
例如，我们已经看过Z_12^*，我们说过Z_12^*中含有四个元素
for example, we already looked at Z twelve
star. We said that Z twelve star contains
1、5、7、11，因此我们说
these four elements, one, five, seven, and
eleven. And therefore we say that phi of
φ(12)只含有四个元素，问你们个问题，φ（P）是多少
twelve is simply the number four. So let
me ask you as a puzzle, what is phi of P?
它是Z_p^*的大小，所以事实上，我们说
It will basically be the size of Z P star.
And so, in fact, we said that in the Z P
Z_p^*含有除了0的所有的Z_p的所有元素。因此
star contains all of Z P except for the
number zero. And therefore, phi of P for
对于任意质数p有φ（p）=p-1。现在，讲一个特例
any prime P is gonna be P minus one. Now,
there is a special case, which I'm gonna
我在这说并且我们之后要用的RSA系统。如果N是由两质数之积
state here and we're gonna use later for
the RSA system. If N happens to be a
那么φ（N）=N-P-Q+1
product of two primes, then phi of N is
simply N minus P minus Q plus one. And let
让我展示给你们为什么，已知N是Z_N^*的大小，
me just show you why that's true. So
basically N is the size of Z N. And now we
现在我们需要移除所有与m不互素的元素。
need to remove all the elements that are
not relatively prime to m. Well how can an
怎么判断一个元素是否和m不互素呢？则它要不被p整除
element not be relatively prime to m? It's
gotta be divisible by p or it's gotta be
或者被q整除。在0到m-1中有多少个元素能被p整除？
divisible by q. Well how many elements
between zero and m minus one are there,
一定有q个，那么有多少个元素能被q整除呢？
there that are divisible by p? Well there
are exactly q of them. How many elements
这一定有p个。
are there that are divisible by q. Well
there are exactly p of them. So we
所以我们减去p来除去那些被q整除的数。我们减去q来除去那些被p整除的数
subtract p to get rid of those divisible
by q. We subtract q to get rid of those
注意到我们减了两次0
divisible by p. And you notice we
subtracted zero twice, because zero is
因为0既是P的除数也是Q的除数。因此，我们加1来保证我们只减了一次0
divisible both by P and Q. And therefore,
we add one just to make sure we subtract
所以不难得到，φ(N)=N-P-Q+1
zero only once. And so it's not difficult
to see that phi(N) is N-P-Q+1. And another way
另一种表达方式是φ（N)=(P-1)*(Q-1），这是我们一会要用到的定理
of writing that is simply (P-1) times (Q-1). Okay,
so this is a fact that we will use later
我们回到之前谈论的RSA系统。目前为止，只是定义了欧拉函数φ
on, when we come back and talk about the
RSA system. So far, this is just defining
但欧拉很好的运用了这个函数φ
this phi function of Euler. But now Euler
put this phi function to really good use.
他证明出这个惊人的事实
And what he proved is this amazing fact
here that basically says that if you give
如果你给我任意一个属于Z-N^*的元素X。事实上，X的φ（N）次方等于Z_N^*中的1，
me any element X in Z N star. In fact, and
it so happens that X to the power of phi(N)
现在你可以明白欧拉定理是费马定理的一个推广
is equal to one in Z N. So you can see
that this is a generalization of Fermat's
特别的，费马定理只应用于质数，我们知道
theorem; in particular, Fermat's theorem
only applied to primes. For primes we know
对于质数p，φ（p）=p-1，换句话说，如果N是质数，那么我们
that phi(p) is equal to p minus one, and
in other words if N were prime we would
简单的计算出p-1，并
simply write p minus one here, and then we
would get exactly Fermat's theorem. The
欧拉定理的美妙在于它不仅适用于质数，还适用于合数，
beauty of Euler's theorem is that it
applies to composites, and not just
让我们来看些例子，看5的φ（12）次方
primes. So let's look at some examples. So
let's look at five to the power of phi(12).
所以5是Z_12^*中的元素。如果我们算出5的φ（12）次方
So five is an element of Z12 star.
If we raise it to the power of five of
那么我们就可以得到Z_12^*中的1，我么知道φ（12）=4,
twelve, we should be getting one. Well, we
know that phi(12) is 4, so we're
我们可以求出5的4次方。5的4次方等于625
raising 5 to the power of 4. Five to
the power of four is 625 and it's a simple
很容易算出5^4等于1模12。这是用例证
calculation to show that that's equal to
1 modulo 12. So this is proof
但不是证明，这只是一个例子
by example but of course it's not a proof
at all. It's just an example. But in fact
但事实上不难证明欧拉定理，事实上，我将告诉大家
it's not difficult to prove Euler's
theorem and in fact I'll tell you that
欧拉定理是拉格朗日定理的特例
Euler's theorem is also a very special
case of Lagrange's general theorem.
我们也说欧拉定理是费马定理的一个推广
Okay so we say that this is a
generalization of Fermat's theorem and
实际上，我们将看到欧拉定理是RSA加密系统的基础
in fact as we'll see this Euler's
theorem is the basis of the RSA crypto
这节课就到这了，我们将在下节课继续
system. So I stop here and we continue
with modular quadratic equations in the
讨论模二次等式的问题
next segment.